<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="amqp.xsl"?>

<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE amqp SYSTEM "amqp.dtd">

<amqp name="transactions" label="the AMQP Transactions Layer">

  <!-- == Section: transactions ================================================================ -->

  <section name="transactions" title="Transactional Messaging">
    <doc>
      <p>
        Transactional messaging allows for the coordinated outcome of otherwise independent
        transfers. This extends to an arbitrary number of transfers spread across any number of
        distinct links in either direction.
      </p>

      <p>
        For every transactional interaction, one container acts as the <i>transactional
        resource</i>, and the other container acts as the <i>transaction controller</i>.
        The <i>transactional resource</i> performs <i>transactional work</i> as requested by
        the <i>transaction controller</i>.
      </p>

      <p>
        The <i>transactional controller</i> and <i>transactional resource</i> communicate over a
        <i>control link</i> which is established by the <i>transactional controller</i>.  The <xref
        name="declare"/> and <xref name="discharge"/> messages are sent by the <i>transactional
        controller</i> over the <i>control link</i> to allocate and complete transactions
        respectively (they do not represent the demarcation of transactional work). No transactional
        work is allowed on the <i>control link</i>. Each transactional operation requested is
        explicitly identified with the desired transaction-id and therefore may occur on any link
        within the controlling Session, or, if permitted by the capabilities of the controller, any
        link on the controlling Connection. If the <i>control link</i> is closed while there exist
        non-discharged transactions it created, then all such transactions are immediately rolled
        back, and attempts to perform further transactional work on them will lead to failure.
      </p>
    </doc>
  </section>

  <section name="txn-declare" title="Declaring a Transaction">
    <doc>
      <p>
        The container acting as the transactional resource defines a special target that functions
        as a <xref name="coordinator">transaction coordinator</xref>. The <i>transaction
        controller</i> establishes a control link to this target. Note that links to the <xref
        name="coordinator"/> cannot be resumed.
      </p>
      <p>
        To begin transactional work, the transaction controller must obtain a transaction identifier
        from the resource. It does this by sending a message to the <xref name="coordinator"/> whose
        body consists of the <xref name="declare"/> type in a single <xref type="type"
        name="amqp-value"/> section. Other standard message sections such as the header section
        SHOULD be ignored. This message MUST NOT be sent settled as the sender is required to
        receive and interpret the outcome of the declare at the receiver. If the coordinator
        receives a <xref type="type" name="transfer"/> that has been settled by the sender, it
        should <xref type="type" name="detach"/> with an appropriate error.
      </p>
      <p>
        If the declaration is successful, the coordinator responds with a disposition outcome of
        <xref name="declared"/> which carries the assigned identifier for the transaction.
      </p>
      <p>
        If the coordinator was unable to perform the <xref name="declare"/> as specified by
        the transaction controller, the transaction coordinator MUST convey the error to the
        controller as a <xref name="transaction-error"/>. If the <xref name="source"/> for the link
        to the <xref name="coordinator"/> supports the <xref name="rejected"/> outcome, then the
        message MUST be <xref name="rejected"/> with this outcome carrying the <xref
        name="transaction-error"/>.  If the <xref name="source"/> does not support the <xref
        name="rejected"/> outcome, the <i>transactional resource</i> MUST <xref name="detach"/> the
        link to the coordinator, with the <xref name="detach"/> performative carrying the <xref
        name="transaction-error"/>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Transaction controllers SHOULD establish a control link that allows the
        <xref name="rejected"/> outcome.
      </p>
      <picture title="Declaring a Transaction"><![CDATA[
Transaction Controller                  Transactional Resource
===============================================================================

ATTACH(name=txn-ctl,          --------->
       ...,
       target=
         Coordinator(
           capabilities=
             "amqp:local-transactions")
      )

                             <--------- ATTACH(name=txn-ctl,
                                               ...,
                                               target=
                                                 Coordinator(
                                                   capabilities=
                                                     ["amqp:local-transactions",
                                                      "amqp:multi-txns-per-ssn"]
                                                            )
                                              )

                             <--------- FLOW(...,handle=1, link-credit=1)

TRANSFER(delivery-id=0, ...) --------->
{ AmqpValue( Declare() ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=0, last=0,
                                                    state=Declared(txn-id=0) )

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
      </picture>
    </doc>
  </section>

  <section name="txn-discharge" title="Discharging a Transaction">
    <doc>
      <p>
        The controller will conclude the transactional work by sending a <xref name="discharge"/>
        message (encoded in a single <xref type="type" name="amqp-value"/> section) to the
        coordinator. The controller indicates that it wishes to commit or rollback the transactional
        work by setting the <i>fail</i> flag on the <xref name="discharge"/> body. As with the <xref
        type="type" name="declare"/> message, it is an error if the sender sends the <xref
        type="type" name="transfer"/> pre-settled.
      </p>
      <p>
        Should the coordinator be unable to complete the <xref name="discharge"/>, the coordinator
        MUST convey the error to the controller as a <xref name="transaction-error"/>. If the <xref
        type="type" name="source"/> for the link to the <xref name="coordinator"/> supports the
        <xref type="type" name="rejected"/> outcome, then the message MUST be <xref type="type"
        name="rejected"/> with this outcome carrying the <xref name="transaction-error"/>.  If the
        <xref type="type" name="source"/> does not support the <xref type="type" name="rejected"/>
        outcome, the <i>transactional resource</i> MUST <xref type="type" name="detach"/> the link
        to the coordinator, with the <xref type="type" name="detach"/> performative carrying the
        <xref name="transaction-error"/>.  Note that the coordinator MUST always be able to complete
        a <xref name="discharge"/> where the fail flag is set to true (since coordinator failure
        leads to rollback, which is what the controller is asking for).
      </p>

      <picture title="Discharging a Transaction"><![CDATA[
Transaction Controller                  Transactional Resource
===============================================================================

TRANSFER(delivery-id=0, ...) --------->
{ AmqpValue( Declare() ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=0, last=0,
                                                    state=Declared(txn-id=0) )

                                  :
                          Transactional Work
                                  :


TRANSFER(delivery-id=57, ...) --------->
{ AmqpValue(
    Discharge(txn-id=0,
              fail=false)
           ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=57, last=57,
                                                    state=Accepted() )

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
      </picture>
    </doc>
  </section>

  <section name="txn-work" title="Transactional Work">
    <doc>
      <p>
        Transactional work is described in terms of the message states defined in <xref type="doc"
        name="message-state"/>. Transactional work is formally defined to be composed of the
        following operations:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p><i>posting</i> a message at a target, i.e. making it <i>available</i></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><i>acquiring</i> a message at a source, i.e. transitioning it to <i>acquired</i></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><i>retiring</i> a message at a source, i.e. applying the terminal outcome</p>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        The transactional resource performs these operations when triggered by the transaction
        controller:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>posting</i> messages is initiated by incoming <xref type="type" name="transfer"/>
            frames
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>acquiring</i> messages is initiated by incoming <xref type="type" name="flow"/>
            frames
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>retiring</i> messages is initiated by incoming <xref type="type" name="disposition"/>
            frames
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        In each case, it is the responsibility of the transaction controller to identify the
        transaction with which the requested work is to be associated. This is done with the
        transactional delivery state <xref name="transactional-state"/> that combines a txn-id
        together with one of the terminal delivery states defined in <xref type="section"
        name="delivery-state"/> of the messaging specification. The <xref
        name="transactional-state"/> is carried by both the <xref type="type" name="transfer"/> and
        the <xref type="type" name="disposition"/> frames allowing both the <i>posting</i> and
        <i>retiring</i> of messages to be associated with a transaction.
      </p>

      <p>
        The <xref type="type" name="transfer"/>, <xref type="type" name="disposition"/>, and <xref
        type="type" name="flow"/> frames may travel in either direction, i.e. both from the
        controller to the resource and from the resource to the controller. When these frames travel
        from the controller to the resource, any embedded txn-ids are requesting that the resource
        assigns transactional work to the indicated transaction. When traveling in the other
        direction, from resource to controller, the <xref type="type" name="transfer"/> and <xref
        type="type" name="disposition"/> frames indicate work performed, and the txn-ids included
        MUST correctly indicate with which (if any) transaction this work is associated. In the case
        of the <xref type="type" name="flow"/> frame traveling from resource to controller, the
        txn-id does not indicate work that has been performed, but indicates with which transaction
        future transfers from that link will be performed.
      </p>
    </doc>

    <doc title="Transactional Posting">

      <p>
        If the transaction controller wishes to associate an outgoing <xref name="transfer"/> with a
        transaction, it must set the state of the transfer with a <xref name="transactional-state"/>
        carrying the appropriate transaction identifier. Note that if delivery is split across
        several <xref name="transfer"/> frames then all frames MUST be explicitly associated with
        the same transaction. It is an error for the controller to attempt to discharge a
        transaction against which a partial delivery has been posted. Should this happen, the
        control link MUST be terminated with the <xref name="transaction-error"
        choice="transaction-rollback"/> error.
      </p>

      <p>
        The effect of transactional posting is that the message does not become available at the
        destination node within the transactional resource until after the transaction has been
        (successfully) discharged.
      </p>

      <picture title="Transactional Publish"><![CDATA[
Transaction Controller                  Transactional Resource
===============================================================================

TRANSFER(handle=0,           --------->
         delivery-id=0, ...)
{ AmqpValue( Declare() ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=0, last=0,
                                                    state=Declared(txn-id=0) )


TRANSFER(handle=1,           --------->
         delivery-id=1,
         state=
           TransactionalState(
             txn-id=0) )
{ ... payload ... }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=1, last=1,
                                                    state=TransactionalState(
                                                            txn-id=0,
                                                            outcome=Accepted())
                                                   )

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
      </picture>

      <p>
        On receiving a non-settled delivery associated with a live transaction, the transactional
        resource must inform the controller of the presumptive terminal outcome before it can
        successfully discharge the transaction. That is the resource must send a <xref type="type"
        name="disposition"/> performative which covers the posted transfer with the state of the
        delivery being a <xref name="transactional-state"/> with the correct transaction identified,
        and a terminal outcome. This informs the controller of the outcome that will be in effect at
        the point that the transaction is successfully discharged.
      </p>
    </doc>

    <doc title="Transactional Retirement">

      <p>
        The transaction controller may wish to associate the outcome of a delivery with a
        transaction. The delivery itself need not be associated with the same transaction as the
        outcome, or indeed with any transaction at all. However, the delivery MUST NOT be associated
        with a different <i>non discharged</i> transaction than the outcome. If this happens then
        the control link MUST be terminated with a <xref name="transaction-error"
        choice="transaction-rollback"/> error.
      </p>

      <p>
        To associate an outcome with a transaction the controller sends a <xref type="type"
        name="disposition"/> performative which sets the state of the delivery to a <xref
        name="transactional-state"/> with the desired transaction identifier and the outcome to be
        applied upon a successful discharge.
      </p>

      <picture title="Transactional Receive"><![CDATA[
Transaction Controller                  Transactional Resource
===============================================================================

TRANSFER(handle=0,           --------->
         delivery-id=0, ...)
{ AmqpValue( Declare() ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=0, last=0,
                                                    state=Declared(txn-id=0) )
FLOW(handle=2,               --------->
     link-credit=10)

                             <--------- TRANSFER(handle=2,
                                                 delivery-id=11,
                                                 state=null,
                                        { ... payload ... }

                                  :
                                  :

                             <--------- TRANSFER(handle=2,
                                                 delivery-id=20,
                                                 state=null,
                                        { ... payload ... }


DISPOSITION(first=11,        --------->
            last=20,
            state=TransactionalState(
                    txn-id=0,
                    outcome=Accepted())
           )

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
      </picture>

      <p>
        On a successful <xref name="discharge"/>, the resource will apply the given outcome and may
        immediately settle the transfers. In the event of a controller initiated rollback (a <xref
        name="discharge"/> where the fail flag is set to true) or a resource initiated rollback (the
        <xref name="discharge"/> message being rejected, or the link to the <xref
        name="coordinator"/> being detached with an error), the outcome will not be applied, and the
        deliveries will still be "live" and will remain acquired by the controller - i.e. the
        resource should expect the controller to request a disposition for the delivery (either
        transactionally on a new transaction, or non-transactionally).
      </p>
    </doc>

    <doc title="Transactional Acquisition">
      <p>
        In the case of the <xref type="type" name="flow"/> frame, the transactional work is not
        necessarily directly initiated or entirely determined when the <xref type="type"
        name="flow"/> frame arrives at the resource, but may in fact occur at some later point and
        in ways not necessarily anticipated by the controller. To accommodate this, the resource
        associates an additional piece of state with outgoing link endpoints, an optional
        <i>txn-id</i> that identifies the transaction with which <i>acquired</i> messages will be
        associated. This state is determined by the controller by specifying a <i>txn-id</i> entry
        in the <i>properties</i> map of the flow frame. When a transaction is discharged, the
        <i>txn-id</i> of any link endpoints will be
        cleared.
      </p>

      <p>
        If the link endpoint does not support transactional acquisition, the link MUST be terminated
        with a <xref type="type" name="amqp-error" choice="not-implemented"/> error.
      </p>

      <p>
        While the <i>txn-id</i> is cleared when the transaction is discharged, this does
        not affect the level of outstanding credit. To prevent the sending link endpoint from
        acquiring outside of any transaction, the <i>controller</i> SHOULD ensure there is no
        outstanding credit at the sender before it discharges the transaction. The <i>controller</i>
        may do this by either setting the drain mode of the sending link endpoint to <i>true</i>
        before discharging the transaction, or by reducing the <i>link-credit</i> to zero, and
        waiting to hear back that the sender has seen this state change.
      </p>

      <p>
        If a transaction is discharged at a point where a message has been transactionally acquired,
        but has not been fully sent (i.e. the delivery of the message will require more than one
        <xref name="transfer"/> frame and at least one, but not all, such frames have been sent)
        then the resource MUST interpret this to mean that the fate of the acquisition is fully
        decided by the discharge. If the <xref name="discharge"/> indicates the failure of the
        transaction the resource MUST abort or complete the sending the remainder of the message
        before completing the discharge.
      </p>

      <picture title="Transactional Acquisition"><![CDATA[
Transaction Controller                  Transactional Resource
===============================================================================

TRANSFER(handle=0,           --------->
         delivery-id=0, ...)
{ AmqpValue( Declare() ) }

                             <--------- DISPOSITION(first=0, last=0,
                                                    state=Declared(txn-id=0) )
FLOW(handle=2,               --------->
     link-credit=10,
     drain=true,
     properties={
       txn-id=0
     })

                             <--------- TRANSFER(handle=2,
                                                 delivery-id=11,
                                                 state=
                                                   TransactionalState(txn-id=0),
                                        { ... payload ... }

                                  :
                                  :

                             <--------- TRANSFER(handle=2,
                                                 delivery-id=20,
                                                 state=
                                                   TransactionalState(txn-id=0),
                                        { ... payload ... }


DISPOSITION(first=11,        --------->
            last=20,
            state=TransactionalState(
                    txn-id=0,
                    outcome=Accepted())
           )

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
      </picture>

    </doc>

    <doc title="Interaction of Settlement with Transactions">
      <p>
        The Transport layer defines a notion of <i>settlement</i> which refers to the point at which
        the association of a delivery-tag to a delivery attempt is forgotten. Transactions do not in
        themselves change this notion, however the fact that transactional work may be rolled back
        does have implications for deliveries which the endpoint has marked as settled (and for
        which it therefore can no longer exchange state information using the previously allocated
        transport level identifiers).
      </p>

      <doc title="Transactional Posting">
        <dl>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Settled By Controller</dt>
          <dd><p>The delivered message will not be made available at the node until the transaction
              has been successfully discharged. If the transaction is rolled back then the delivery
              is not made available. Should the resource be unable to process the delivery it MUST
              NOT allow the successful discharge of the associated transaction. This may be
              communicated by immediately destroying the controlling link on which the transaction
              was declared, or by rejecting any attempt to discharge the transaction where the fail
              flag is not set to true.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Unsettled By Controller; Resource Settles</dt>
          <dd><p>The resource MUST determine the outcome of the delivery before committing the
              transaction, and this MUST be communicated to the controller before the acceptance of
              a successful discharge. The outcome communicated by the resource MUST be associated
              with the same transaction with which the <xref name="transfer"/> from controller to
              resource was associated.
            </p>
            <p>
              If the transaction is rolled back then the delivery is not made available at the
              target. If the resource can no longer apply the outcome that it originally indicated
              would be the result of a successful discharge then it MUST NOT allow the successful
              discharge of the associated transaction. This may be communicated by immediately
              destroying the controlling link on which the transaction was declared, or by rejecting
              any attempt to discharge the transaction where the fail flag is not set to true.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Unsettled By Controller; Resource Does Not Settle</dt>
          <dd><p>Behavior prior to discharge is the same as the previous case.</p>
            <p>
              After a successful discharge, the state of unsettled deliveries at the resource MUST
              reflect the outcome that was applied. If the discharge was unsuccessful then no
              outcome should be associated with the unsettled deliveries. The controller SHOULD
              settle any outstanding unsettled deliveries in a timely fashion after the transaction
              has discharged.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </doc>
      <doc title="Transactional Retirement">
        <p>
          Here we consider the cases where the resource has sent messages to the controller in a
          non-transactional fashion. For the cases where the resource sends the messages
          transactionally, see <b>Transactional Acquisition</b> below.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Unsettled By Resource; Controller Settles</dt>
          <dd><p>Upon a successful discharge the outcome specified by the controller is applied at
              the source. Should the controller request a rollback or the discharge attempt be
              unsuccessful, then the outcome is not applied. At this point the controller can no
              longer influence the state of the delivery as it is settled, and the resource MUST
              apply the default outcome.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Unsettled By Resource; Controller Does Not Settle</dt>
          <dd><p>The resource may or may not settle the delivery before the transaction is
              discharged. If the resource settles the delivery before the discharge then the
              behavior after discharge is the same as the case above.
            </p>
            <p>
              Upon a successful discharge the outcome is applied.  Otherwise the state reverts to
              that which occurred before the controller sent its (transactional) disposition. The
              controller is free to update the state using subsequent transactional or
              non-transactional updates.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </doc>
      <doc title="Transactional Acquisition">
        <dl>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Settled By Resource</dt>
          <dd><p>In the event of a successful discharge the outcome applies at the resource,
              otherwise the acquisition and outcome are rolled back.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>Delivery Sent Unsettled By Resource; Controller Sends Outcome</dt>
          <dd><p>An outcome sent by the controller before the transaction has discharged MUST
              be associated with the same transaction. In the even of a successful discharge the
              outcome is applied at the source, otherwise both the acquisition and outcome are
              rolled back.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </doc>
    </doc>
  </section>

  <section name="coordination" label="types used to interact with a coordinator node">
    <type class="composite" name="coordinator" source="list" provides="target"
          label="target for communicating with a transaction coordinator">
      <doc>
        <p>
          The coordinator type defines a special target used for establishing a link with a
          transaction coordinator.
        </p>
      </doc>

      <descriptor name="amqp:coordinator:list" code="0x00000000:0x00000030"/>

      <field name="capabilities" type="symbol" requires="txn-capability" multiple="true"
             label="the capabilities supported at the coordinator">
        <doc>
          <p>
            When sent by the transaction controller (the sending endpoint), indicates the desired
            capabilities of the coordinator. When sent by the resource (the receiving endpoint),
            defined the actual capabilities of the coordinator. Note that it is the responsibility
            of the transaction controller to verify that the capabilities of the controller meet its
            requirements. See <xref name="txn-capability"/>.
        </p>
        </doc>
      </field>

    </type>

    <type class="composite" name="declare" source="list"
          label="message body for declaring a transaction id">
      <doc>
        <p>
          The declare type defines the message body sent to the coordinator to declare a
          transaction. The txn-id allocated for this transaction is chosen by the transaction
          controller and identified in the <xref name="declared"/> resulting outcome.
        </p>
      </doc>

      <descriptor name="amqp:declare:list" code="0x00000000:0x00000031"/>

      <field name="global-id" type="*" requires="global-tx-id" label="global transaction id">
        <doc>
          <p>
            Specifies that the txn-id allocated by this declare MUST be associated work with the
            indicated global transaction. If not set, the allocated txn-id will associated work with
            a local transaction. This field MUST NOT be set if the Coordinator does not have the
            <xref name="txn-capability" choice="distributed-transactions"/> capability. Note that
            the details of distributed transactions within AMQP 1.0 will be provided
            in a separate specification.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </field>
    </type>

    <type class="composite" name="discharge" source="list"
          label="message body for discharging a transaction">
      <doc>
        <p>
          The discharge type defines the message body sent to the coordinator to indicate that the
          txn-id is no longer in use. If the transaction is not associated with a global-id, then
          this also indicates the disposition of the local transaction.
        </p>
      </doc>

      <descriptor name="amqp:discharge:list" code="0x00000000:0x00000032"/>

      <field name="txn-id" type="*" requires="txn-id" mandatory="true"
        label="identifies the transaction to be discharged"/>

      <field name="fail" type="boolean" label="indicates the transaction should be rolled back">
        <doc>
          <p>
            If set, this flag indicates that the work associated with this transaction has failed,
            and the controller wishes the transaction to be rolled back. If the transaction is
            associated with a global-id this will render the global transaction rollback-only. If
            the transaction is a local transaction, then this flag controls whether the transaction
            is committed or aborted when it is discharged. (Note that the specification for
            distributed transactions within AMQP 1.0 will be provided separately in Book 6
            Distributed Transactions).
          </p>
        </doc>
      </field>
    </type>

    <type class="restricted" name="transaction-id" source="binary" provides="txn-id">
      <doc>
        <p>
          A transaction-id may be up to 32 octets of binary data.
        </p>
      </doc>
    </type>

    <type class="composite" name="declared" source="list" provides="delivery-state, outcome">
      <doc>
        <p>
          Indicates that a transaction identifier has successfully been allocated in response to a
          declare message sent to a transaction coordinator.
        </p>
      </doc>

      <descriptor name="amqp:declared:list" code="0x00000000:0x00000033"/>

      <field name="txn-id" type="*" requires="txn-id" mandatory="true"
             label="the allocated transaction id"/>
    </type>

    <type class="composite" name="transactional-state" provides="delivery-state" source="list"
          label="the state of a transactional message transfer">
      <doc>
        <p>
          The transactional-state type defines a delivery-state that is used to associate a delivery
          with a transaction as well as to indicate which outcome is to be applied if the
          transaction commits.
        </p>
      </doc>

      <descriptor name="amqp:transactional-state:list" code="0x00000000:0x00000034"/>

      <field name="txn-id" type="*" mandatory="true" requires="txn-id"
             label="identifies the transaction with which the state is associated"/>
      <field name="outcome" type="*" requires="outcome" label="provisional outcome">
        <doc>
          <p>
            This field indicates the provisional outcome to be applied if the transaction commits.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </field>
    </type>

    <type class="restricted" name="txn-capability" source="symbol" provides="txn-capability"
          label="symbols indicating (desired/available) capabilities of a transaction coordinator">

      <choice name="local-transactions" value="amqp:local-transactions">
        <doc>
          <p>
              Support local transactions.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="distributed-transactions" value="amqp:distributed-transactions">
        <doc>
          <p>
              Support AMQP Distributed Transactions.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="promotable-transactions" value="amqp:promotable-transactions">
        <doc>
          <p>
              Support AMQP Promotable Transactions.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="multi-txns-per-ssn" value="amqp:multi-txns-per-ssn">
        <doc>
          <p>
              Support multiple active transactions on a single session.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="multi-ssns-per-txn" value="amqp:multi-ssns-per-txn">
        <doc>
          <p>
              Support transactions whose txn-id is used across sessions on one connection.
          </p>
        </doc>
      </choice>
    </type>

    <type class="restricted" name="transaction-error" source="symbol" provides="error-condition"
          label="symbols used to indicate transaction errors">
      <choice name="unknown-id" value="amqp:transaction:unknown-id">
        <doc>
          <p>The specified txn-id does not exist.</p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="transaction-rollback" value="amqp:transaction:rollback">
        <doc>
          <p>The transaction was rolled back for an unspecified reason.</p>
        </doc>
      </choice>

      <choice name="transaction-timeout" value="amqp:transaction:timeout">
        <doc>
          <p>The work represented by this transaction took too long.</p>
        </doc>
      </choice>
    </type>
  </section>

</amqp>
